Hello.
How nice.
We would be gathered here to talk about the coming legislation-
-And what it can mean for you who work locally.
The reason we have this session, it is both to capture the ER-
-It's the beginning of a needs inventory of how we should design our support to ER-
-If the future legislation.
It's a way for us to start ...
"This is what we think."
You can give feedback.
How right do you think we end up in our discussions?
Before we start, I'll introduce ourselves on stage.
My name is Charlotta Gustafsson, I am from the Crime Prevention Council.
I thought we were doing a short recap on the law, which is proposed.
There maybe Greta, Håkan and Malin want to fill up, but I'm starting a bit.
The law does not describe what a municipality should do, but more how a municipality should work.
It is both a strength and a weakness so clearly.
What you print a lot in the bill is that you have to work knowledge -based.
There should be a situation picture, which includes both a survey-
-A causal analysis and an information about the conditions one has-
-To prevent crime.
Based on the situation, one should formulate-
-The action plan, ie how to work with the questions-
-And after every two years do a follow -up of the work.
-Have I missed something?
-No.
I can say briefly too ...
... that the information I have received from Justitie and Skr-
— will the Law Council's remit be ready before the election-
-And the bill will be completed after the election.
The law is expected to enter into force on July 1, 2023, for those who do not know.
As Morgan said this morning, there is quite a great agreement around this law.
-Over party borders.
-Yes exactly.
Should we start by looking at how you have answered ...
Are you with us, Lars?
... on the survey.
So far you had answered ...
The support that Brå and also the county administrative boards and the police provide to the municipalities-
-would be able to develop.
So you can develop the crime prevention work.
We have been negative to a legislation-
-But it is because we do not like the state controlling the municipalities.
It is more of such a aspect that we put in it.
Now we understand that we do not escape legislation.
Then it is more about how the state actors should support the municipalities-
-And what money will we get for this?
These are the issues we are now running.
From a crime prevention perspective-
-Can it have an effect, and you can get a mandate for the questions in a different way.
The municipalities are obliged to work with this.
Getting this as uniform as possible.
That we work in the same way in the country.
I think we have to safeguard municipal self -government.
We develop the crime prevention work by based on local conditions.
Speaking of local conditions, we have received a question where one wonders-
-If we can explain more what we mean by knowledge -based.
We say the situation that includes survey, causal analysis.
"Have you had thoughts about the situation image as a basis for priorities"-
-"Out of what should be included? Is it a difference it would be good to have it explained."
From how we previously talked about situation pictures and what is in the legislation.
If there is a difference.
There is someone who says: "Good, Greta."
I'm just trying to be your speech tube.
-Do you want to answer the question?
-It's clear you should check the difficult.
Actually, there is not much difference to what is in the law text.
We have said that a situation picture should contain a survey and an analysis.
Then we have not quite as clearly talked about inventing their conditions-
-Working crime prevention.
I don't know if you can see the spin in front of you.
That it says "initiate collaboration" at the top.
But one has to identify what it looks like organizationally to us.
What are we doing now?
What kind of structures do we have?
What can we use?
-With such information, and I think that is important.
I believe that if we get this base-
-when the legislation approaches, then the idea is that the work we put there-
-Do lead to something better than what we have done before, to the right action.
That is the very purpose of this.
The purpose is not collaboration-
-The position pictures or mapping.
The purpose is to get one step further through the tools.
It takes time.
Many of us here in the room have been doing this for years.
My hope is that we will be able to take the step and get a little better.
Get a little sharper, put in a little better action against what is actually the problem.
The collaboration for the sake of collaboration is meaningless.
We must never forget why we do this.
Not to get the complete position image-
-A of the crime prevention work.
We see how other types of crime categories are starting to become more and more interesting-
-At national level.
It is about environmental crime, it is about men's violence against women, the business issue.
Very interesting in relation to the crime prevention work-
-But also violation of welfare.
This clarifies the complexity-
-In the crime prevention work.
The new bill presses a little neighbor.
Where you really show the importance of the entire municipality working crime prevention.
Many administrations have to enter this work and can contribute in a good way.
Both in a mode of image work-
-But also linked to solving the crime problems.
Cause analysis means to dive deep into a problem.
How can it be part of a situation picture?
I would like to say that a situation can ...
The survey will cover everything you have found.
But in the situation picture you also try to identify more as pattern-
-and make a compilation of their survey.
This means that you can prioritize certain crimes.
"This is what we want to know more about and do causal analysis about."
We do not say that one should do a causal analysis of all-
-An if you can report a survey that has covered a lot.
In this way, I think that the causal analysis will be included in the position image.
I hope I do not say to what we have written in the book.
Based on the situation, it is assumed that the collaborative parties-
-which is identified in this legislation, make its prioritization first-
-When which are our most important problems we see?
-And how the municipalities work according to it.
We will follow up on it-
-And I suspect it will be like the annual report we do today.
It may be a bit like open comparisons, which Skr develops.
That you describe how the municipalities work.
But we have no sanctioning authority.
We are not such an authority.
We will only compile this.
There is no sanction, and it thinks that Skr is good.
We also do not think that the state should control exactly what the municipality does-
-Or I think the municipalities want to do right.
The municipalities want to work as well as they can in the crime prevention work.
Then these must be anchored from above.
Not MD the priority that the security and security issues have in the municipalities.
Fifteen years ago, these issues were not on the agenda as they are today.
Now almost all municipalities talk about this.
Then you prioritize it differently, depending on what the crime looks like in the municipality.
It will be a cue in to the next question.
We have received a question.
It is in itself good with national unity and structure-
-But are there any thoughts with us about how to support the smaller municipalities?
They often have small resources and limited presence of police.
In the bill, the county administrative boards also have ...
It states that we must be allocated funds to provide operational support to municipalities-
-To reach the requirements of the legislation.
-When we talk support.
There I can fill up, in the annual report I talked about earlier in day-
-That we see a development-
-There of metropolitan municipalities since 2017 have been high and stable.
They have fairly good conditions organizationally to work with the questions.
They have a habit of doing mapping, causal analysis and follow -ups.
Then we have also followed the smaller municipalities, which we will support.
You can see that the curve is going up now.
There are more people who have local advice.
More who have collaboration agreements.
Smaller municipalities may not allocate a full-time service to this question-
-Thaly combines it with several other prevention issues.
You may not have had a pure education for the questions either.
Despite this, you still do surveys.
It goes up.
It is more causal analysis, a little weaker with follow -up, but it is a positive trend.
But you look at the medium-sized municipalities-
-When we barely talk about, but that are still quite a few in Sweden-
-The their curve is more flat.
In some respects, it has now begun to go down.
When we said we need to look over all the municipalities-
-blie the "big city, socially vulnerable areas, gang crime"--
-Or it will be sparsely populated, and so we have lost middle milk Sweden.
It may be coincidences that make it flicker out.
It can be a result after the restrictions of Covid-19.
But we have to keep extra eyes to the medium -sized municipalities.
The county administrative boards' regional crime prevention coordinator-
-Find out throughout the country.
We adapt our work based on the needs that exist in our county.
That communication is important.
Contact the coordinator on the county administrative board.
Have a dialogue about what support you want, what support the county administrative board can provide.
It is also a way for us that, just as Lotta talked about earlier in day-
-Being able to bring up the local level on a national level.
Then we have to get it to us in order to pass it on.
No, exactly.
This is a collaboration-
-Which is to be based on agreeing on what to work with.
Then you have to file on ...
After all, there are municipalities that do not want to be part of the citizen promises-
-like the police.
Municipalities have broken the cooperation agreement-
-To you are dissatisfied with the police's representation.
Then you have to try to find ... The very basis of the agreement-
-Is, as Charlotta says, a kind of will.
If one cannot agree on one point, it cannot be included in the agreement.
If one is dissatisfied with the police presence-
-Do not regulate the agreement.
What we can do better together in this work, we will work with that.
Hopefully, in a collaboration, one can agree-
-What to be included in the agreement, and not.
If you cannot agree on a particular issue, you should not bring it.
Neither the municipality nor the police can force the other to sign an agreement.
The important thing is to have this collaboration and that you try to move on.
Then you have to take a new hold the next time you negotiate or sit down and plan.
Hopefully it is not a document that you hit the other in your head.
It should be a common will, which controls the work forward.
We should be a little better together.
It should not be a bat, a threat or a bribe.
That is not the purpose.
The purpose is for us to get better.
That the municipality and police find the right measures.
The police will take into account the municipality's picture of reality and vice versa.
It's a hard question-
-But the very purpose is not to have it as a bat.
We can't force anyone else, simply.
Before I give you the word I want to say, good Malin!
-1-1.
-Now it's me zeroing.
"Do you do the homework according to the book 'Collaboration in local crime prevention work'"-
-Harms the agreement at the level that both parties have the opportunity to work with.
-But also many police officers who are dissatisfied with the municipality.
It looks very different, who is drawing in this work.
What becomes more equal is-
-This is that both the police and the municipality have a crime prevention assignment by law.
That's the difference now.
Previously, the police have had the mission-
-And the municipalities have been involved to the extent that they want or need.
Now it becomes a kind of minimum requirement.
Both have the assignment.
It may be able to help us get this balance that both parties weigh just as heavily.
It is very important in collaboration, that it is not the one or the other who has the power.
The police should not dictate the conditions for the municipality.
There are two equivalent parties who will agree and work towards a common goal.
So it's longed for this.
We promise that we will stand up for.
-Bra, Håkan.
-Yes.
Good, Håkan.
All you municipalities that have received these indications, this is a fellow
-That police legislation does not change.
They are responsible for this question-
-No like we will get it in the municipality.
You have to take it into consideration, and then you have to have Håkan's words in the back-
-That it's a joint job.
The police should not reverse, but take a step forward.
There you have to be a little responsive to the way the situation looks out-
-And you get to talk to your police locally, and what you have expectations.
We have talked a lot on the county administrative boards.
What we get from the municipalities-
-The coupled to the police, is very much about ...
We believe that there will be greater demands on collaboration with the police.
The municipalities will demand it, more will demand it.
Part of it will be about the statistics, getting statistics from the police.
That police officers should feel comfortable with what statistics they can disclose.
It is a dialogue we have had long before this bill came too.
There, the police are very clear about "that we should get it".
There should be a clarity around it.
It is that all municipalities say they need support-
-But it looks very different what kind of support you need.
This is what will be the challenge for us at national level-
-Finding the right level of support.
I think the county administrative boards will play a big role in this.
One municipality in one county may need one type of support, another municipality another.
Then you have to be responsive to it and adapt it to the needs that exist.
I think there are different levels, but also in different ways at the different levels.
Everyone does not say "we need support with mapping or training".
It looks very different.
The municipality's work looks very different.
It reflects the multifaceted work that is to be based on the local problem picture.
That it looks different, and that we work in different ways-
-But that the common should be the structure and that we can achieve success.
-To support your local crime prevention.
They exist, as well.
We have a tradition of working with that and we are pretty good at that.
We need to bring politicians and managers on this-
-and that they understand what the law will mean.
What does it mean to give an assignment to reach to produce a position image-
-So that they really understand what they order and allocate resources in relation to it.
I want to make a little bet that Brå is now, together with the county administrative boards-
-even SKR and the police are involved on a corner-
-Developing an education for managers and politicians.
We feel that there is a strong need to clarify this.
Someone has written in the chat and wants to tip about a course at Linnaeus University-
-which is called "Crime prevention methods and collaboration".
That training is open to police, municipality and county administrative boards-
Many of the things come again.
Any thoughts about it?
Many of the fears are interesting, and you have to try to work with it.
But I think too-
-That most municipalities want to do right.
I usually try to say that to the county administrative board-
-When sometimes think the municipalities are trying to throw away.
"The municipalities do not want to throw away. They want to do right for themselves."
This is no exception.
I think you will do after best
-To work this way and work forward on this issue.
We should not get stuck in the legislation.
It becomes in some way like a wall.
The idea is that we should be behind the legislation.
Move on to work.
-Where it doesn't already exist today.
I think we have to bring with us ... If you look at how far we have come-
-In the crime prevention work, without legislation-
-As by having produced support and having a crime prevention counsel-
-And how far we have come.
Almost all municipalities in the day-
-Have some type of cooperation supervision.
We do some type of survey.
We do a lot of work that is in the right path.
We have achieved this without legislation.
We must have that with us - that we do this.
This is not difficulty for us, we have done this before.
We know this.
There is a lot of support to get and the state wants us to do this now.
That's not how it's intended.
This is an indication of where we are going.
If you have not come all the way then, I do not think it is the whole world.
It is a work that we have to build on.
They should be better, year by year.
That's the idea.
Even though the law says a certain level-
-We can develop the work.
-An better transition.
-Right?
Then we have the last question we asked in the survey:
"What will be better thanks to the law?"
Just.
There I think we could see two slightly larger areas.
Partly it is about this work with bf-